Finding Aid for Women's Crisis Center (Ann Arbor, Mich.) Records, 1971-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Women's Crisis Center (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1971-1990
Women's Crisis Center (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
0.5 linear ft.
93835 Bk 2
Women's support group founded in 1971 to aid and counsel victims of rape and abuse. Background materials, coordinator's files, publicity files, and visual materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group (Donor no. 8012 ) was transferred from the Women's Studies Program of the University of Michigan in February 1992.
The record group is open to research.
The idea of a Women's Crisis Center (WCC) for victims of rape was conceived in the Fall of 1971 after a series of rapes on the north side of Ann Arbor. Founded by Marnie Heyn as an agency to aid victims of rape and abuse and to provide counseling service, the WCC began operation on November 16, 1971 in offices on the second floor of the Michigan Union. Practical services provided by the Center included legal aid, emergency medical assistance for rape and assault cases, contraceptive information, abortion counseling, suicide prevention, and drug help. In response to the recent rapes, the Center organized volunteer squads of four women to patrol campus areas at night and established "crisis aid stations" to serve as refuge for women followed or harassed on the street. Because of a controversy between the Michigan Union Board and the Office of Student Services over the authority to locate space in the Union, the first WCC had to disband.
On April 24, 1972, the WCC was reestablished with its office in the basement of St. Andrews Episcopal Church at 306 N. Division St. It moved in February 1976 to a new location at 325 E. Summit and again in February 1977 to 211 1/2 N. Fourth Avenue, sharing the second floor with "Womanspace," a feminist bookstore. In the Fall of 1982, the Center moved back to St. Andrews Church.
The reestablished WCC continued many of the practical services provided in 1971 but also had more general aims and was concerned about the role of women in society. Its basic objectives in the 1970s were to reduce anxiety for women in crisis situations by providing counseling and practical assistance and by encouraging women's self-help and personal growth through continuing education.
In meeting some of its goals, the WCC sponsored conferences on "Women and the Law," "Female Sexuality" and "Employment Opportunities for Women," and supported the organization of Assault Crisis Centers (ACC) in Ypsilanti and Ann Arbor to handle all counseling and direct services to victims of rape and domestic violence in Washtenaw County. Other accomplishments of the WCC included the creation of a Task Force called the Rape Education Committee and the publication in 1973 of Freedom from Rape, a 16-page pamphlet dealing with myths about rape. Also of some significance, the women of the Center took part in the Michigan Legislative Task Force on Rape which wrote a model rape law and lobbied for its passage in the State Legislature. The new law - Michigan Criminal Sexual Conduct Act, Public Act 266 - took effect on April 1, 1975.
In the 1980s, the WCC continued its operation of a 12-hour-a-day hotline for women needing help with problems ranging from domestic violence and sexual assault to finding transportation or a place to live. In addition, the Center also served as a field placement for students in women's studies, psychology, and social work. Women of the Center were involved in the Citizen's Advisory Committee of Rape Prevention (CACORD) and Ann Arbor Coalition Against Rapes (AACAR), an association that organized self-defense workshops and an annual march, "Take Back The Night." In 1987-1989, the WCC published Free Women's Words, a "free bi-monthly Women's newsjournal."
The WCC ceased operation in September 1990.
The records of the Women's Crisis Center (WCC) document the goals and activities of this organization in Ann Arbor during the 1970s and 1980s. The bulk of the collection consists of press articles about rape in Washtenaw County, training manuals, and other documentation given to the volunteers of the WCC. The records are divided in four series: background materials, coordinator's files, publicity files, and visual materials.
Subjects:
Abused women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Rape victims--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women's Crisis Center (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Women's shelters--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Billboards.; Rapes.; Streets--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Background Materials
  The first series, Background materials (1974-1989), consists of leaflets presenting the WCC, its history and activities. Included as well are training manuals used by the staff of the Center.
  - Histories of WCC, undated (Box 1)
  - By-laws and code of ethics, 1974, 1981 and undated (Box 1)
  - Training and recruitment brochures, undated (Box 1)
  - Manuals, 1985, 1989 and undated (Box 1)
- Coordinator's files
  In the series of Coordinator's files (bulk dates 1984-1990) are minutes from the very last period of the WCC (December 1989-August 1990). Phone lists provide the names of the staff women between 1984 and 1988.
  - Administration: Financial report, 1974-1975; Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Staff: Phone lists, 1984-1988; Public service announcements, 1985-1990 (Box 1)
  - Contacts: Legislation and relationship with local authorities, 1972-1989; Address lists, undated; Correspondence, 1972-1988 (Box 1)
- Publicity files
  Publicity files (1971-1989) - the largest series of the collection - document the organization of ads campaigns. Included are press releases, press clippings of the local newspapers about women and especially about rape, and notes detailing the publication of Free Women's Words in 1987. There is also a collection of flyers from the 1980s announcing center activities.
  - Organization of ads campaigns; includes Manuals and address lists, undated (Box 1)
  - Press releases, 1972-1989 (Box 1)
  - Press cuttings, 1971-1987 (Box 1)
  - Free Women's Words; includes Notes on publication, September 1987 and Graphics by Laurie Jo Wechter and Kasha Fluegge, 1984-1987 (Box 1)
  - Flyers, undated (Box 1)
- Visual materials
  The series of Visual materials (1981?-1985?) consists of photographs and slides mainly taken as part of a presentation about the work of the Center. Included are views of the WCC office and of various areas of Ann Arbor (probably where assaults occurred).
  - Photographs; includes Office of the WCC, undated; Tee-shirt of the WCC, 1981? and Wimmin at Greenham Peace Camp, Blue Gate, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Slides, 1985?, 3 boxes (Box 1)
    (includes views of Ann Arbor probably used in slide presentation about the work of the WCC)